I'm Mike Massimino, a
former NASA astronaut.
I was with NASA for 18 years,
and my primary job was to be a spacewalker
on the Hubble Space Telescope.
And this is everything I'm
authorized to tell you.
Everyone says, "Adios,"
and then they close the
inner hatch and lock it.
So now they're getting rid
of all the air in the airlock
until it goes down to vacuum.
Even though I'd been in
space for a couple days,
I felt there was a really big difference
between being inside of a spaceship
and going outside of it.
You know, like, that's
space out there, man.
The only thing that's
protecting me is my spacesuit.
And it was like this door, you know?
It's the door to space.
In the shuttle days, we had
two categories of astronauts.
We had astronaut pilots who
were military test pilots
or former military test pilots.
And their primary job
was to operate and fly
the vehicle, land it,
because it landed like a glider
or like an aircraft on a runway.
I was a mission specialist.
My job was to do all the other stuff.
Do the space walks, work the robot arm,
do the experiments,
help with the systems
of the space shuttle.
My primary responsibility on
both of my flights, though,
was to be a spacewalker.
My first mission, we trained
for a year and a half.
My second year,
we ended up training for
two and a half years.
It was only supposed to
be a year and a half.
You're training the whole time,
as far as NASA is concerned,
you're hired as an astronaut candidate
or as the experienced
people like to call you,
you're an ASCAN, or we are the ASCANs.
We need something done around here.
And you don't get that title astronaut
until you complete the training program.
And then you successfully
graduate from that.
It usually takes about two years,
and you get a silver astronaut pin.
And then when you fly in space,
you get a gold astronaut pin.
So after being at NASA for four years,
I was assigned to my first flight.
And then it was about another
year and a half after that
until I flew that flight.
For Hubble, it was learning about systems
and also learning more about
how the shuttle is going
to be used for the flight.
And then the space walk.
You train specific space walks
and specific robotic
operations for your flight.
There's different facilities to do that,
where, like, there's an air-bearing floor
where you're moving things around.
It's kind like an air hockey table,
so the thing kind of floats,
and you're moving around.
But it all kind of comes
together when you go to the pool.
You'd get into your space suit
and be put in the pool,
and they would weigh you out.
Meaning that they would get
the right amount of flotation
and weights for you to
be a neutrally buoyant.
Meaning the force of gravity
and the buoyancy force of
the water kind of evens out,
and you're floating in the water column,
similar to the way you'll
be floating in space.
And then you run the space
walk from start to finish.
100 feet wide, it's 200 feet
long, and it's 40 feet deep.
It is a really big pool.
So the Hubble missions,
they used to call us the prima donna crew,
and everyone in the
office would would call,
"Oh, you're prima donnas."
And I liked that.
That was cool, because
yes, we are special.
And the reason they called us that
is because of the support we had.
It was a huge team of people,
not only at the Johnson Space Center,
but also from the Goddard
Space Flight Center.
So we had a lot of support.
So back in the day when we
were doing lots of space walks,
building a space station,
and going to Hubble,
they would have what we called dual ops.
So you would have two crews in there.
The training in the pool was really good
to get you ready to do your job.
I felt very prepared when I got to space.
At the end of my first space walk,
I remember closing an equipment bay door
and realizing that I felt like
I had done that task 100 times,
even though I had never been in space.
Toilet on the shuttle
required some training
to just get your aim correctly
because it was a small
hole on the commode.
So you would pee into a hose
and that was pretty easy to do that.
But the commode on the shuttle
was a bit complicated
in a very small opening.
So the deal was you had to
practice your alignment.
And the way that worked is we
had, in our simulator area,
we had a toilet that worked
just like the shuttle toilet.
And so you could practice on that one.
You could poop into that thing.
You made sure you call them to tell them,
"Hey, it's time to come service that."
'Because it wasn't a flush toilet.
It would contain the material.
So to practice for that,
there was another toilet right next to it
that you did not poop in.
But that was like an alignment trainer
and that had a camera
looking up through the hole.
And it had a close
circuit TV right over here
that they promised that that
was not going anywhere else.
And then memorize that
position on the toilet,
like, you know, I felt,
oh, I'm riding a chop,
you know, and a motorcycle.
I felt like, all right, that was a feeling
of kind of leaning back.
And then you'd kind of memorize that
and then you could actually try it out
and see how well you did on the real one
that was next to you.
They don't usually tell
anybody about that.
You know, it's like a deep
dark secret that you have:
to align your butt
correctly over the commode.
The night before my first
launch, I was pretty excited,
anticipating everything.
You're in crew quarters with your crew.
You're in quarantine.
You do get able to see your family,
whoever's cleared by the doctor.
The night before, you get
to eat whatever you want.
I remember, Lady Dot was her name,
who was head of kind of
running crew quarters
down there at the Kennedy
Space Center said to me
they were going to go shopping
and asked me what I wanted for dinner.
I was like, "Whatever you have, Dot.
It's all good here. I don't care.
She goes, "I think you can have
anything you want tonight."
And I go, "Well, whatever
you have was fine with me."
And she looks at me and grabs my hand.
She goes, "Honey, you're going
on a rocket ship tomorrow.
You can have anything
you want to eat tonight."
And I was like, "OK,
Dot, how about a steak?"
So you wake up and you get dressed.
Usually you have a crew shirt picked out
because you're going to
get your picture taken
as a crew at breakfast.
There's a cake there.
That's a kind of a
tradition to have a cake
whether or not you want
a piece of cake or not,
but they'll have a cake there for you.
Every crew member has a
technician helping them
that you've trained with
throughout your training flow
whenever you have the suit
on for your training events.
And so they're there
and you get the suit on,
get your pocket stuffed with whatever.
The commander plays a hand of poker
with the head of the office,
the head of the astronaut office,
until the commander loses
to leave all your bad luck on the planet.
Charlie said, "Mike, come
over here and join us."
And I played poker with Charlie
and Scooter, our commander.
And one of our crew mates was
like, "Whoa, what's going on?
This is bad luck.
You can't have an extra guy in there."
Scooter eventually lost and
we headed to the launchpad.
For me, the biggest moment of fear
was before my first launch,
looking at the spaceship in the night sky.
It's fully fueled and making noises
and water vapors coming off of it,
but you know, it looks like
there's smoke coming off of it
and it looked a little intimidating.
So I thought maybe this
wasn't such a good idea,
but by then it's too
late and you have to go.
So the shuttle had a
flight deck with windows
and instruments and stuff to look at
and there was four people up there.
And then there were three
of us on the mid deck,
which really not much to look at,
except these lockers in front of us.
And we did have an altimeter
to tell us, you know,
what the pressure was
inside of our spaceship.
So all the action was on the flight deck.
So we played like tic-tac-toe
and rock, paper, scissors
sitting next to each other,
that kind of thing.
Then it's a couple minutes,
and then it's one minute and 30 seconds.
And then the spaceship
is starting to come alive
at that point.
With a couple minutes to go,
they start up the auxiliary power units.
And then six seconds, the engine start,
and the whole stack leans
forward and then comes back.
You still haven't gone anywhere yet
until the solid rocket boosts
the two big white rockets
on either side.
And once they light, you're moving.
You haven't yet cleared the tower.
You're still going a hundred miles an hour
as soon as you take off and
you accelerate from zero
to 17,500 miles an hour about
eight and a half minutes.
You feel the acceleration.
The g-force start to build up.
There's a lot of shaking going on.
With the solid rockets still attached,
they run for two and a half minutes
and they run rough because
there's solid material.
The g-force build up to about 3G.
So three times your body
weight is what you're feeling.
So I felt like there
were like three big dudes
sitting on me.
And then at the end of
eight and a half minutes,
the main engine's cut and your weightless
and then the feeling
is just weightlessness
where there's no more forces on you.
My arms just floated up like this
because that happens naturally.
You're kind of glad that you made it.
Your first day, I didn't feel good.
I threw up my first day in space.
You get stomach awareness
because your inner ear is trying to...
Your brain's trying to
figure out what's going on
because your inner ear works on gravity
and there's no gravity when
you're in orbit affecting you.
So your brain doesn't
know what's going on.
And so it's a conflict between
the inner ear and the eyes,
which leads to nausea.
Sometimes sickness or air sickness.
That kind of thing you might get in a car
as, you know, car sickness.
I was fine by the second day.
My second flight,
I think my brain remembered
to kicked right in
and I was OK from the get go.
But on day three is when we rendezvoused.
You had a laser which
shoot off for distance
and speed measurements
and make sure all the
computers were working
and we were getting closer.
So you get it really
close to the telescope.
You see it like a star in
the distance, you know,
the beginning of the day
and you're getting closer and closer.
The way we grabbed the telescope
is we would get it with the robot arm.
When you're docking with the
International Space Station,
it's like a docking port
that docks with a...
On, you know, one side of it
on the spacecraft that's coming.
And then the other side
on the space station.
On Hubble, you had to grab it,
and then we would go to a free drift,
which means that no more
flying the spaceship.
And that also means that you
don't have that much time.
Because if you wait too long,
the arm mechanics of the two vehicles
will start to separate.
So you know, you have a couple
minutes to go and get it.
And then we'd place it
on a big turntable we had
at the back of the space shuttle.
So it would then be brought
down into those latches
and we would latch it to the shuttle
and then we could remove the arm
and then we would apply power to it.
We had an umbilical
that would give it power
and we could get data from it and so on.
So that's what we would do.
Then once it's attached,
it's not going anywhere
and it's powered so it's
going to stay alive.
And then we're going to go start
our space walks on day four.
Columbia was my first mission.
It was in March of '02.
The next launch for
Columbia was STS-107 flight
and that was in January of 2003.
On launch, they took some damage
that they didn't know about.
We didn't have a way to detect it,
but they took a piece of
debris off the external tank,
the big fuel tank.
Put a hole in the wing,
which they didn't know about.
We didn't find this out until after
with the post-flight analysis.
And when they tried to
reenter the atmosphere,
it was a hole in the wing.
He came in the wing, we
lost a vehicle in the crew.
So that was a bad day.
I knew them really well.
Three of them were classmates of mine.
The others, I knew really well.
Ilan Ramon was a Israeli astronaut
who my family and I
became very close with.
Still close with his kids.
And then the others, the other folks,
Rick Husband was a very
good friend of mine,
one of my better friends,
one of my best friends in the office.
He was the commander.
And there were two others from
the class previous to mine.
So I knew them all really well.
I was actually taking my
son to a boy scout event
and one of the parents
kind of took me to the side
and said they had heard something.
And then I called one of
my buddies who was at home
and said, "Hey, turn on the
TV and see what's going on."
And he said, he's like,
"We got to go to work."
You know, I talked to my family about it.
You know, we knew it was a risky business
and that this didn't add
any new information really.
It wasn't like a surprise
that this could happen.
And in a weird way,
it's kind of like, well,
you know, this happened
and it's probably not going
to happen again for a while.
We're going to have to be really careful
and make sure it doesn't happen again.
But I still wanted to go
and I got the support
I needed from my family
to give it another try.
I still have great confidence in NASA.
Things are going to happen
every once in a while
where the environment is going to win
and you're going to have
a bad day, unfortunately.
I think that all of us
tried to think of everything
that could go wrong
and try to have a solution for it.
And everything that did go
wrong, we had a solution for.
But there's always those things
that you can't even imagine happening.
And everything kind of happens,
boom, boom, boom, boom, boom, on that day
where, you know, there
may be 10 different things
that happened that are unique,
but they all happened at
the same time together.
And that's when you have a bad day.
Things happen.
You know, on the most recent mission,
the Artemis II mission,
there was talk about the heat shield.
But they knew about that threat,
and they studied and tested
and did everything they could.
So I was pretty convinced
that this is not going to be
a problem, the heat shield.
They were going to have a problem.
It's going to be something
no one thought of,
and be like, "Ooh, we didn't
know that can happen."
I have high confidence
in the way they operate.
I had the sense that on my
first flight, maybe foolishly,
that the major danger was over,
and we made it to orbit, which
was certainly in your face.
This, you could get killed.
And the space walks, we
had to be really careful.
We talked about it,
that we thought the second
most dangerous thing
we were going to do was the space walks.
And so not that we shouldn't have known
that entry coming back could be dangerous.
It just seemed like that was not...
We weren't going to
have a problem with it.
I was convinced we were going to be OK.
And so when we had the
accident, the Columbia accident,
it was a reminder
that, you know, you're not safe again
until you're back on Earth.
The Hubble space walks were considered
to be the most complex,
meaning that there was so
many things you had to do.
So it wasn't just built to be
a telescope and sent to space.
It was built to be serviced.
So just about everything
could be taken out of there.
The solar arrays were in
clamps and with connectors
so you could undo the
clamp, undo the connectors,
remove the solar array, put a new one in.
The Hubble Space Telescope
is about the size of a school bus,
a standardized school bus.
It's that size
because it was made to be
as large as it could be
and still fit in the payload
bay of the space shuttles.
All of the instruments,
some of them are the
size of a refrigerator,
some of them the size
of a baby grand piano,
all of those things could be
removed by undoing some latches
and some connectors,
removing it very carefully,
putting a new one in, and
taking the old one home.
And that was generally the drill.
It was a dream of astronomers for years
to get a telescope into space.
Because even on the clearest
night at a very high altitude
where the atmosphere is thin,
you're still looking
through the atmosphere.
When that starlight
comes in, it's distorted,
and that's why stars twinkle,
because it's distorting of the light.
So "Twinkle, Twinkle Little Star"
is written by someone on Earth,
because when you're in space,
you don't get that twinkling.
There are perfect points of light.
Hubble's above our atmosphere
and can look directly into the universe
and is able to return
these beautiful images.
Telescope was launched back in 1990.
We only go into Hubble a few times.
Well, on space station,
there's always a crew there.
They could do a space walk
if they need it, you know, tomorrow
if something's going wrong,
but there's no crew on Hubble's.
You only can go out for a
certain amount of space walk.
We did five on each one of my missions.
We had two different teams trading off.
We would get a lot of attention.
"Hey, we need a new tool to
do this," and we would get it.
Our pistol grip tool,
this power tool we had was developed
for the Hubble missions
and it was used to also
build the space station.
Helmet cameras.
See all these helmet camera views you get
from these space walks?
Well, that was a Hubble thing.
They didn't have those things before
because what they used to do on Hubble
is when they would close the doors,
when you would work inside
and close the doors,
you had to do these closeout photos,
which you physically have
a camera looking around,
it took a long time.
So what they did is they had the idea
to put cameras on your head
so that as you're doing the space walk,
you know, they could get all
the information they needed
about what it looked like inside of there.
And that was then turned over as well
to the other missions that
were not going to Hubble.
So we had just about everything
we needed and wanted.
And there were years in the making.
You wake up and the
spacewalkers have first dibs
on the toilet that day
because there's only one toilet.
So you always want to
have a good breakfast
because there's no food
inside of the space suit.
The only nourishment you had,
you had a 32 ounce bag of
water inside of there with you.
So that was it.
And put your diaper on first.
Then you put these
polypropylene underwear on
to absorb your sweat.
And you put some socks
on, keep your feet warm.
And then you put a liquid
cooling garment on,
which is like a fancy
pair of long underwear
with lots of tubes on it.
And so that's to bring the
cooling water over your body.
You're typically more
concerned about getting too hot
because you're in an enclosed
space suit that cannot leak
or else you have trouble.
So you have something to suck the air in
to the life support system in your feet
and in your arms.
And that air will go in
and get scrubbed for
CO2 and other particles.
And then the fresh air is
going to come in over your head
through the helmets.
And then you start a pre-brief.
So in our missions,
we had about 40 minutes
of breathing 100% oxygen.
You're going to go to a
lower pressure in the suit.
We lowered the pressure in the vehicle.
We could do this on the shuttle
where you could lower the pressure
from 14.71 atmosphere, like sea level,
down to 10.2, which is like
being on a tall mountain.
What that does is that helps rid the body
of some of its nitrogen.
So you don't want to get the
bends, decompression sickness.
If you're in a higher pressure environment
and then you immediately go to
a lower pressure environment,
it could lead to some
neurological problems
because the nitrogen in your system
can cause trouble in the bloodstream
and that's not good.
There's a hatch that leads
to space, which is locked
or else you have a big hole in the space
if you know that.
But there's the inner hatch
that's open up to that point
where, you know, you got
in there and everything.
And then, you know,
everyone says, "Adios,"
and then they close the
inner hatch and lock it.
So now they're getting rid
of all the air in the airlock
until it goes down to vacuum.
Those moments where you're in there
with your space walking buddy,
kind of looking at each
other a little bit,
just kind waiting to go outside,
thinking about maybe your first thing
you're going to do, whatever.
And I remember my first
time looking at that hatch.
And even though I'd been
in space for a couple days,
I felt there was a really big difference
between being inside of a spaceship
and going outside of it.
You know, like that's
space out there, man.
The only thing that's
protecting me is my spacesuit.
And it was like this door, you know?
That's the door to space.
Typically, it's an experienced
person and a new person.
So on my first flight was
a guy named Jim Newman
who had space walk many times
before and other missions.
So he went out first and made
sure the coast was cleared,
got our tethers set up and
he got everything ready.
The telescope is not
that far away from you.
It's out in the payload bay
and about maybe 50 or
60 feet away from you.
So it's not that far
away from the airlock.
Once the airlock goes to vacuum,
the only thing you're hearing
is what's coming over your com cap.
It's kind of peaceful.
And you hear in the background,
you hear like this hum.
It's the air pump water separator.
It's like a little fan that goes
and it keeps the cooling pump going
and the ventilation going.
This miraculous small little pump.
There's one spacewalker's
on the robot arm,
and that means the robot
arm operator's going to move
the spacewalker around.
The other person is what
we call the free floater
and they're moving
around with their hands,
moving around this way,
and they can climb all over the place.
You have a safety tether
attached to the arm
in case you start floating away.
But that's not going to happen.
So the way to get out to the telescope
is you go along the side
of the space shuttle.
There's handrails that get you out there.
And then he said, "All right, Mike,
you're clear to come out."
And he stuck my head out of the airlock
and he's up on a handrail on the bulkhead,
the forward bulkhead of the
shuttle looking down at me.
He had his visor up so
I could see his face.
And it was, you know, he's
got this big smile on his face
and above his head is Africa.
So the thought that went
through my mind was,
"Whoa, how am I going to
get anything done out here?"
In front of me,
there was a handrail for the space shuttle
and the curved handrail above the airlock.
And there was a foot restraint here,
just like there wasn't a training pool.
There was a vent duct coming on each side.
And I was like, "I know what I'm doing.
I'm going to rely on my training here
and start off that way."
I mean, you're out in space.
You know, you see the planet,
and it's just unbelievable.
I remember the first time,
one of my first tasks the
first time I was out there,
I was got into the robot arm
and went up high on the telescope.
And so I was getting, you know,
taken up on the telescope,
just riding along.
And I could see down
then as I got up high.
I could see down over
the wing of the shuttle
and I could see the NASA meatball
and Space Shuttle Columbia
name and the American flag
and looking in the planets
out in the distance.
And the first space walk I was
on kind of went really well.
Everything was working
and we were humming along
and sticking to business.
Everything was working,
going according to plan.
We actually got a little bit ahead.
We finished everything we were
supposed to a little early.
You feel pretty, pretty drained.
It's a mental exercise too.
You're out there.
You plan the space walk to be
about six and a half hours.
And then the ones I had, I
think were all longer than that,
like more like around seven and change.
And it's pretty intense.
Physically, I was in the
best shape of my life
before each one of my missions.
So I was pretty well prepared
physically to do these things.
But still, it's pretty draining.
I mean you're pretty beat
when you get back in from your space walk.
And you get out of there.
You know, you're ready to clean up
and get something to eat.
- [Interviewer] What's the protocol
if an astronaut starts floating
away from the space shuttle?
- There is a protocol if
you start flowing away.
You always have to have
your safety tether hooked up
just in case somehow you
came off the structure
or came out of the robot
arm or something like that.
That safety tether will take care of you.
It's a titanium piece of cord.
If that came undone,
then you're a free flyer,
then you're out of luck.
And that's never happened.
But if it did,
on the space station,
you have a little jet pack you could fly,
that you could fly back to the...
Because they can't come
get you at space station.
You can't undock a
vehicle to come get you.
It's unlikely anyway.
But if you came undone,
you would fly yourself,
you had a little jet pack.
But we didn't have that on Hubble.
But if that happened,
you start floating away,
become a free flyer,
and you can't get back.
The commander would then come and get you.
Since we were space
walking on the shuttle,
you could still fly the shuttle around.
He would take over the
controls of the shuttle
and fly it to you so you would grab it.
We called it the lost
crew person procedure.
And we would brief it
just to go through it.
Because it's like an emer-
Lost crew person is what you do.
But my friend Rick
Linnehan on my first flight
had a bit of a dark sense of humor, maybe.
You're in space, and he's
briefing us for the first time.
All these saying you know,
"You tether this," and blah blah blah.
And he goes, "Lost crewperson.
Don't worry about it.
We got two more inside."
So the second mission to Hubble,
what ended up being the final mission,
we knew it was going to
be the final mission,
and no one's been there since,
and we were trying to
do as much as we could.
Second mission, STS-125
was in 2009, May of 2009.
There were two instruments
that had power failures,
and they couldn't turn these things on,
but you know, they were great instruments,
and we did not have replacements for them.
One of these two
is called the Space Telescope
Imaging Spectrograph
that could do things like
analyze the atmospheres
of far of planets.
And they wanted to bring
this capability back.
Now these things were put
together over years in time
by really conscientious
engineers and technicians.
Their goal was to make it
so no one could ever
take this apart again.
It was buttoned up
so that there would be no
danger to it during launch.
It could withstand launch
and the rigors of space
and no one was ever going
to open these things again.
This panel had 111 small screws,
each of which had a washer.
And just to make sure the
screws never back out,
they put glue on the threads.
But that task alone, over
100 new tools were designed.
So I was the lead spacewalker
and had a fellow out there
with me, was a new guy.
Mike Good, my good buddy
and a great spacewalker.
So we practice and practice,
and we practiced working
together of every little step
of everything we were going to
do to repair the instrument.
You were doing this
really delicate procedure
with these gloves on,
and the tools are designed to make it
so the gloves will work with them.
So if you had, like, a regular tool
that you might be familiar
with, like a crescent wrench,
that thing will have an extra
added handle piece to it.
Some special space rubber stuff,
hard material that'll
allow you to use the tool
without having to have a death grip on it
like you would on Earth.
I felt you're, like,
trying to work on your car,
like change the oil in the
car, with boxing gloves.
It was the most ambitious
space walk we've ever tried.
Capture plate on there.
Just gets all these little screws.
And to do that, we had
to remove four screws
on the outer side of this.
The easiest thing I was
going to do that day
was remove a handrail
that was used to insert the
instrument years earlier.
That handrail had two
big screws at the top,
two big hex screws at the top,
and two big hex screws at the bottom.
So we weren't worried about those screws.
They were beefy.
And we even used the old power tool.
We didn't even need any fancy stuff,
and it was just going to
take, like, 30 seconds.
There's one line in the checklist.
It was so simple. We had
no recourse for this.
Like, even I couldn't mess it up.
The one at the bottom left
comes loose, you know?
I could feel that.
The one at the bottom right,
it's just spinning my tool.
And I was like, "What's going on?"
And I removed the tool, and
I look with my helmet light,
and I bend down and I look,
and it's no longer a hex head.
It's gnarled that piece of metal.
And I realized, holy cow.
That screw's never coming out.
Handrail's not coming off.
111 screws aren't coming out.
We'll never replace the power supply.
We're not going to bring
the instrument back to life.
We'll never find out if
there's life in the universe.
And everyone's going to blame me.
That wasn't far from the
situation at that moment.
Before I said anything,
I just kind of leaned
out of the telescope,
because I was working in there,
and I leaned out, and we
were over the Pacific Ocean,
and I thought to myself,
I can't even get to a
hardware store if I wanted to.
Like, I've really messed up this time.
I don't know what we're going to do.
And for about an hour or
so, we were troubleshooting,
and I didn't have any good idea.
I mean, I was trying to think,
what else could we remove?
What other tools could we try?
Could we get it from the back?
And oh, I knew it was bad,
because I knew the repair
backwards and forwards,
and I knew that there's
no way to get around this.
But we had a clever
engineer named Jim Corbo.
He thought to himself,
what would he do if he was in his garage?
What would you do at home?
He said, "Sometimes brute
force is the answer."
He would just try to rip that thing off,
because it was loose at the top, you know?
You'd just yank it and break it.
And he called over to the
Goddard Space Flight Center,
and they're standing by, you
know, watching this in horror.
That years of, hours of training for this
and all the aerial development tools
have just gone up in smoke.
They were watching, and
Jim told them their idea
and they came up with was the idea
to pull an instrument out of a clean room,
put it in the same
configuration with the handrail,
and they pulled on the top of
the handrail with a fish scale
to see how hard it would
be to break that bolt
at the bottom that was still there.
And it broke that bolt
at 60 pounds of force.
Tony told me afterwards,
he was worried about breaking that
and debris going flying and
hitting, getting me or Mike.
You break stuff in space,
you're asking for trouble.
Shrapnel or sharp edge
or something like that.
If you have a projectile coming flying
because you just broke a piece of metal
and it hit my spacesuit
or bueno spacesuit,
it could cause a real problem.
The technique they wanted us to use,
which was not to just yank it,
but to kind of break,
like kind of just not yank
the whole thing off at one,
but try to like weaken it,
you know, kind of yield it a little bit
and then in a couple steps get it
so it just need a little tug at the end.
It all went perfectly after that.
So this space walk went pretty long.
It was over eight hours,
but we got it all done,
and they brought the
instrument back to life,
and I was just so happy.
I remember we went back to the airlock
and Scooter, Scott Altman, my commander,
was my very good friend,
comes over the communication line
and he says, "Mass, what are you doing?"
And I was like, "Oh, I'm just, you know,
cleaning up the airlock a little bit."
And he goes, "Is there
anything you're doing now
that you can't do later?"
And he goes, "Why don't
you just go outside
and enjoy the view?"
After this, you know, psychic trauma
that I went through breaking
that bolt, stripping that bolt,
you know, so I was just
able to really relax,
and I just let go and took in the view.
And it was a day pass, it was daytime.
We were over to Pacific
kind of heading over Hawaii
and it was just magnificent
seeing the ocean and the clouds.
If we didn't get that handrail removed,
we would've not brought
that instrument back.
And it's still working today.
NASA approached me and said,
"We have this idea to
send a tweet from space."
They asked my commander
about it and he said, "OK."
And they thought I was
the right guy to do it
for whatever reason.
I was like, "OK."
But I didn't have a Twitter account.
I wasn't paying attention
to anything really about
except the mission at that time.
First tweet from space,
I didn't think about it very much.
I just kind of, whatever came to mind.
I didn't think. I didn't know.
I should have thought
about it some more maybe,
but I wrote, "Launch was awesome.
The adventure of a lifetime has begun."
Something like that.
And that was on a Monday.
They made fun of me on
"Saturday Night Live."
Seth Myers was doing weekend update
and he said, "We have the first
treat from space and it is:
'Launch was awesome.'
In 40 years, we've gone from,
'One giant leap for mankind,'
to, 'Launch was awesome.'"
And then he went on to say,
"If we ever encounter
life in the universe,
I assume this is how I'll be notified."
And it shows my Twitter thing that says,
"Geez, dudes. Aliens."
So I got made fun of.
My kids' thought it was cool though.
The first one was a
little, maybe not the best,
but I think they got better.
After my first mission,
the space station
developed the possibility,
the capability of a phone
call that you could make.
There was an internet protocol phone.
You can't call the space station,
but the space station could call you.
If you ever get a phone call, folks,
and it's 281 with a 244
exchange, pick it up.
It might be the space station calling.
'Because if you don't pick it
up and they leave a message
like, "Ah man."
Then you got, "Hey, email me."
You know, they go to email.
"Call me again, will you?"
I was like, "I don't know if
this is such a good idea,"
because we're really busy.
You know, the missions,
we don't have a lot of free time.
The space station you
get like some time off
because you're up there,
you're living up there.
So our families knew we had this.
We never used it.
We didn't even set the thing up.
So then when we got back from
my second fight, you know,
our family was like, "Glad you're back,
but why didn't you call?"
And we set up the expectation we had.
I knew that was a bad idea.
The landing day's pretty exciting.
It's kind of bittersweet because
you know you're coming home
and you know, you've had a good mission,
but you're also excited about coming home.
So that's a good part of it.
And you get ready that day.
It's all about, you know,
preparing the space shuttle to come back
and get your space suits on,
get everything set up,
and go over the briefings.
My first mission, this was
before the Columbia accident.
I know we were moving along
and going through the checklist,
but there wasn't the same
sense of urgency or intensity.
After we had the accident
on entry with Columbia,
then my second flight, which was after,
there was a little more
intense feeling, I think,
about what we were facing.
And we should have had that same intensity
on the first flight,
but for me, it wasn't there.
We were coming in on kind
of a sloping kind of path
across the planet to come in.
So it was pretty smooth.
And you're landing on a runway,
so that was pretty smooth as well.
My first flight we landed
at the Kennedy Space Center,
which is the preferred place
because that's where
you're going to take off.
It was going to leave from the next time.
My second flight though,
we had bad weather at
the Kennedy Space Center
so we got a couple extra
days in orbit, which was fun.
But then they eventually
had to bring us home
and it was still bad weather
at Kennedy Space Center.
So that second flight,
we landed at Edwards Air
Force Base in California.
Weather's always good there.
There were really only
three approved runways.
We had some emergency landing
sites coming up the East Coast
and over in other places.
If you couldn't make it to space
and you can make it across the Atlantic,
in Southern Europe and in Northern Africa,
there were landing sites as well.
But the primary landing sites,
the primary one was the
Kennedy Space Center.
The second one was Edwards Air Force Base.
The third one was White
Sand's Missile Range.
You're going to feel a little off balance
because now your vestibular
system is kicking in again
after being silent for
the past two weeks or so.
So just feeling a little off balance.
You know, you kind of
walk around with your legs
like Frankenstein sort of, you know,
kind of walking around there
with leg spread apart to keep
your balance as best you can
and just kind of getting used
to being back on the planet again.
You got to be careful your first waking up
your first day back on the planet,
that you don't just float out of bed
or try to float out of bed.
I dropped the bag of groceries
in a second day back in the driveway.
Kind of purposely put it up here behind me
and forgot where I was, yeah.
I dreamt about being an astronaut
when I was six years old
and I saw Neil Armstrong on the moon.
I wanted to grow up to be just like him.
He was my hero.
But then I found out I
was afraid of heights,
and trying to grow up
to be like your hero,
like how do you do that?
That's impossible.
So when I was a senior in college,
I went to the movies
and saw this movie, "The Right Stuff,"
which is about the
original seven astronauts
and the test pilots that came before them.
And it made me want to grow
up to be an astronaut again.
The hardest thing about being an astronaut
is getting the opportunity,
because so many qualified
people are trying to get it,
and it's not easy.
And it's kind of out of your
control to a certain extent.
I applied for the class of 1990
and got rejected outright
for the class of '92
and got rejected outright.
The class of '94, which ended
up being the class of '95,
I got an interview with for that class.
When you already get to the interview,
there are thousands of people that apply,
and they typically would
interview about 120 people
over the course of a few months.
But that's a pretty big cut.
And they'd come in for the physical,
and a lot of people were getting DQed
because of the eye test.
So that's what happened to me,
and I said, "Well, there's
no way to get around this."
And then I was pretty disappointed.
But then I started asking questions.
Bob Overmyer was a Marine Corps pilot
who was my boss at McDonnell Douglas.
And he said, "How'd it go?"
And I said, "I got DQed."
And he goes, "It was your eyes?"
And I said, "Yeah."
And he goes, "You know
what you got to do."
I said, "No."
He said, "You got to dehydrate yourself
before you take that test."
I was like, "Really?
He said, "Yeah."
I go, "Why is that?"
He goes, "Well, you know,
you get all the water out of the eye,
and it flattens the eye,
and it focuses differently."
And he goes, "That's what I used to do."
He's a Marine Corps pilot, you know?
And he goes, "You know,
you should try that."
And I go, "Oh, OK, maybe
there's something there."
Next couple hours, that afternoon,
at the Johnson Space Center,
I'm walking through the hallway,
my friend Kevin Kregel is there,
and he's an Air Force test
pilot who's an astronaut.
And he goes, "How'd it go?"
"I got DQed."
He goes, "Your eyesight?"
I go, "Yeah."
He goes, "You know what
you got to do, don't you?"
And I go, "What's that?"
He goes, "You got to
drink a lot of water."
Can you imagine?
You can't make this up.
I'm like, "What?"
And he says, "Oh, it makes
the eye more viscous,
and it bends the light."
And I'm like, "Well, no one
knows what they're doing here."
So maybe there's some
way to get around this.
I don't know if LASIK existed,
but probably not even then.
But there were, like,
procedures you could have done,
and that was lifetime-banning.
So that wasn't a good idea.
When I saw the astronaut job,
that was to me the
opportunity of a lifetime.
And I was not going to stop.
Even if I couldn't get
the medical issue solved,
I would keep trying to get it solved.
I wasn't going to give up.
I found out about this training
in this NASA flight docs,
you know, the doctors were like,
"Well, we think it's hocus-pocus
because, you know,
you just can't really
train your eyes to do that,
but go ahead, you know?
We don't care.
It doesn't do anything to your eye."
And the doctor had told me that,
the eye doctor did, it was
only going to work with kids.
So she didn't think it was going to work.
But I told her I could be really immature.
And then she said, "OK."
You know, she helped me,
and I was able to pick up a couple lines
just so I could try again.
The eye exercise was kind of,
it was kind of like trying
to learn how to focus
beyond what you were looking at.
You're kind of training your eyes to relax
and almost focus beyond
what they're looking at.
And then the letter or the number
or whatever it's that you're
trying to see off a chart
will come into view.
And it's also other things you can do
like wearing under-corrected lenses
so that your eyes are
working a little bit more.
It's like training the brain to just relax
and kind of look beyond
what it's looking at
to try to have things
that normally wouldn't be
in focus come into focus.
I am really excited about the moon.
I've been hoping we've sent people there
since I became an
astronaut, even before that.
I was down at the launch
for the Artemis II flight,
and the Kennedy Space Center
is unbelievable right now.
And I think to realize that,
you had needed to have been
there before, like years ago.
What's happened in the last few years
is now you have these
launches of satellites.
Sometimes you have two
launches in one day.
You know, over a hundred
launches last year.
With all the communication satellites
and some space probes,
mainly communication satellite's going up
and then crews are going up,
not all that often, but
a couple times a year.
They are building things.
Blue Origin has a humongous
building down there
and they're building a
vehicle assembly building.
SpaceX is for their giant Starship.
It's huge.
It looks futuristic,
all the new buildings
that are coming online
and the launchpads that they're using.
And they're using them.
I mean it's like there's launches
almost every day down there.
So it's almost like a
futuristic space port down there
and it's just growing.
It's going to get more and more active.
So I think there's a lot there.
We might hear about the Artemis missions
because those are very
interesting to people.
People go into the moon,
but there's a lot of launches going on.
Still our launches going to
the International Space Station
with crews,
and I think the future is going to be...
The International Space
Station low Earth orbit,
the hope is that'll get turned over
to commercial space stations to utilize.
When I started teaching 13 years ago,
you know, it was starting to get started,
but we weren't sending people
to space on commercial rockets
and now we are.
Commercial space flight
really didn't exist that much.
A lot has changed.
They were talking about all these
things they were going to do.
The commercial companies and
bringing the booster back
and using it again and landing it.
It was like, "Oh, see what happens."
When I saw the first one of those landing
back at the launchpad
and then landing it on a barge
out in the ocean at night,
that is incredible.
So I was really impressed with that.
The reusability of it is what's
going to make it affordable.
The commercial space sector
that has grown immensely
over the past 12 years or so.
And I think that's probably
the biggest difference
between what was going on
and what I'm talking
about in the classroom
compared to all those years ago.
The NASA program itself,
we've kind of cut back.
There was more astronauts
when I was there,
and now there are fewer astronauts
who were on flight status
because there's not as many
of them going into space.
Hopefully that cadence will pick up a bit
now that we're going to the moon
and we're still going to
the space station right now.
Some of the research
that's been done in space
on the space station
has really come around.
They've been able to use
a microgravity environment
for some great research
and commercial activities,
but it's a bit dangerous
sending humans to these places.
So whenever you can, use a robotic device.
I think that's a good idea.
I think there's a still a practical reason
for people to go to space.
That is we're able to do things that...
Still, we're able to do
things that robots can't do
or even with AI.
We can make decisions based on experience.
For example, on a planetary surface,
especially the rovers on Mars,
you know, they don't go very fast
and don't carry a lot of ground.
Over like a period of 10 years,
you can get with maybe,
I don't know what the
exact correlation would be,
but in much less than that time.
If you had a person walking around,
you could cover that same ground.
I'm a professor at Columbia
Mechanical Engineering
and I teach classes that
are related to space flight,
introduction to human space flight,
aerospace human factors.
I teach art of engineering,
which is for new students.
And for the mechanical
engineering section,
we build rockets.
We just launched them last weekend.
That was kind of fun.
So I teach those classes.
I advise the space club,
which is quite active.
We have 500 students.
About 250 or so are active
doing different projects
from rockets to space flight experiments
to high-altitude balloons
to all kinds of things.
So that's pretty enjoyable.
We're starting an aerospace program there.
We have a minor,
and we're starting a major
in aerospace engineering.
So it's taking the first steps for that.
Now I've got my first book.
"Spaceman" is more of a memoir,
and then, it is a memoir.
New York Times bestseller, did well.
I also have a junior, like a
young reader version of that.
And then I have another book, "Moonshot,"
which came out more recently.
It's kind of like my top 10
lessons learned as an astronaut.
It's more in the self-help space.
If NASA calls me tomorrow
to go to the moon,
my answer is yes,
but I can guarantee you
they won't be calling.
So I'm going to be staying
here, I think, on the planet.
Hi, I'm a producer on Authorized Account.
If you enjoyed this video,
then please subscribe and
comment with more topics
that you'd like us to
cover in this series.